Oren Tsur Curriculum Vitae

Contact

Email(s): orentsur@bgu.ac.il

INFORMATION Homepage: www.ise.bgu.ac.il/OrenTsur

Profile

Assistant Professor (Senior Lecturer) at the Department of Software and Information Systems Engineering at Ben Gurion University of the Negev (joined September 2017).

My research mainly involves Computational Linguistics and Social Dynamics. I'm interested in data driven modeling of the processes in which language is shaping and shaped-by social dynamics. In particular, I'm interested in modeling social coordination, influence and contagion in social networks and in the political domain. Beyond the scientific pursuit, this line of research is highly applicable with bearing on sentiment analysis, dialogue systems, virality, cyber security and digital forensics.

Patents: Two patents were filed based on my research by the Hebrew University.

Recent Awards/Fellowships: The NSF Political Network Fellowship for 2014 (grant); The NSF Political Network Fellowship for 2015 (grant); The NSF Political Network Fellowship for 2016 (grant).

15 minutes of fame: Our work on sarcasm detection was featured in Science magazine and was chosen by TIME magazine as one of the 50 best inventions of 2010 (and the only software entry).

Other works were featured in other various popular/scientific outlets such as Science Magazine, The BBC, The New Scientists, The Atlantic, CNET, Gizmodo, Politico and the Boston Globe Magazine.

RESEARCH INTERESTS (AS BUZZ WORDS) Computational Linguistics, Natural Language Processing (NLP), Social Dynamics, Social Networks, Influence and Network Dynamics, Political Networks, Information Diffusion, Sentiment Analysis, Indirect Speech (acts), Discourse Modeling, Pragmatics, Information Retrieval, Data Mining, Machine Learning, Data Science, Big Data, Computational Social Science.

RESEARCH PAPERS (PEER REVIEWED)

ConStance: Modeling Annotation Contexts to Improve Stance Classification

Kenneth Joseph, Lisa Friedland, William Hobbs, David Lazer and Oren Tsur Proceedings of Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP), 2017

On the Interpretability of Thresholded Social Networks

Oren Tsur and David Lazer

Proceedings of the 11th International AAAI Conference on Webl and Social Media (ICWSM), 2017

Voters of the Year: 19 Voters Who Were Unintentional Election Poll Sensors on Twitter

William Hobbs, Lisa Friedland, Kenneth Joseph, Oren Tsur, Stefan Wojcik, and David Lazer Proceedings of the 11th International AAAI Conference on Webl and Social Media (ICWSM), 2017

A Frame of Mind: Using Statistical Models for Detection of Framing and Agenda Setting Campaigns

Oren Tsur, Dan Calacci and David Lazer

Proceedings of the 53rd annual meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), 2015

Don't Let Me Be #Misunderstood: Linguistically Motivated Algorithm for Predicting the Popularity of Textual Memes

Oren Tsur, Ari Rappoport

Proceedings of the 9th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM), 2015

Automatic Discovery of Partisan Campaigns, Agenda Setting and Political Spin in Press Releases

Oren Tsur, Dan Calacci and David Lazer

3rd Symposium on Computation and Journalism (C+J), 2014

As Long as You Name My Name Right: Social Circles and Social Sentiment in the Hollywood Hearings

Oren Tsur, Dan Calacci and David Lazer

Proceedings of ACL Joint Workshop on Social Dynamics and Personal Attributes (ACL), 2014

Efficient Clustering of Short Messages into General Domains

Oren Tsur, Adi Littman and Ari Rappoport.

The 7th International AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media (ICWSM), 2013

Authorship Attribution of Micro-Messages

Roy Schwartz, Oren Tsur, Ari Rappoport and Moshe Koppel

Proceedings of Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP), 2013

Scalable Multi Stage Clustering of Tagged Micro-Messages

Oren Tsur, Adi Littman and Ari Rappoport. (short)

Proceedings of the 22nd International World Wide Web Conference (WWW), 2012.

What's in a Hashtag? Content based Prediction of the Spread of Ideas in Microblogging Communities

Oren Tsur and Ari Rappoport.

Proceedings of the fifth ACM international conference on Web search and data mining (WSDM), 2012

Enhanced Sentiment Learning Using Twitter Hashtags and Smileys

Dmitry Davidov*, Oren Tsur* and Ari Rappoport.

Proceeding of the 23rd international conference on Computational Linguistics (COL-ING), 2010

(*)Both authors equally contributed to this paper.

ICWSM - A Great Catchy Name: Semi-Supervised Recognition of Sarcastic Sentences in Product Reviews

Oren Tsur, Dmitry Davidov and Ari Rappoport.

Proceeding of AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media (ICWSM), 2010

Semi-Supervised Recognition of Sarcastic Sentences in Twitter and Amazon

Dmitry Davidov*, Oren Tsur* and Ari Rappoport.

Proceeding of Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL), 2010 (*)Both authors equally contributed to this paper.

RevRank: A Fully Unsupervised Algorithm for Selecting the Most Helpful Book Reviews

Oren Tsur and Ari Rappoport.

Proceeding of AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media (ICWSM), 2009

Using Classifier Features for Studying the Effect of Native Language on the Choice of Written Second Language Words

Oren Tsur and Ari Rappoport.

Proceedings ACL 2007 Workshop on Cognitive Aspects of Computational Language Acquisition, 2007

BioGrapher: Biography Questions as a Restricted Domain Question Answering Task

Oren Tsur, Maarten de Rijke, and Khalil Sima'an.

Proceedings ACL 2004 Workshop on Question Answering in Restricted Domains, 2004

The University of Amsterdam at the TREC 2003 Question Answering Track V. Jijkoun, G. Mishne, C. Monz, M. de Rijke, S. Schlobach, and O. Tsur.

Proceedings TREC 2003

Abstract based

TALKS/POSTERS:

The Truth About Cats and Frogs - Modeling Information Diffusion of Racist Memes

Oren Tsur and David Lazer

NetSciX, 2017

Money talks - Discovering Latent Connections Between Campaign Contribution and Expressed Agenda in American Congress

Oren Tsur, Navid Dianati and David Lazer

NetSciX, 2017

Are U.S. Political Networks Really Polarized?

Oren Tsur and David Lazer

9th Political Networks Conference, 2016

The Interpretability of ERGM models for Thresholded Networks

Oren Tsur and David Lazer

9th Political Networks Conference, 2016

Put Your Mouth where Your Money Is: Connecting FEC contributions to political speech

Navid Dianati, Oren Tsur, Navid Dianati and David Lazer 9th Political Networks Conference, 2016

Semantically Coordinated Networks in the Political Domain

Oren Tsur and David Lazer 8th Political Networks Conference, 2015

Separated by a Common Language? Using Topic Models in Reconstructing Networks of Political Influence and Cooperation

Oren Tsur, Dan Calacci and David Lazer 7th Political Networks Conference, 2014

In the Name of Love: Revisiting Naming Networks in the Hollywood Hearings (HUAC) Using NLP and Sentiment Analysis Techniques

Oren Tsur, Dan Calacci and David Lazer.

International Sunbelt Social Network Conference, 2014

Mining Complex Networks from Official Congressional Biographies

Brian Keegan, Oren Tsur, Ryan Kennedy and David Lazer.

Workshop on Information in Networks, 2013

Professional Activities

Organizer:

- 2nd workshop on Natural Language Processing and Computational Social Science (ACL 2017)
- Workshop on Natural Language Processing and Computational Social Science (Web Science 2016)
- Workshop on Natural Language Processing and Computational Social Science (EMNLP 2016)
- Joint Workshop on Social Dynamics and Personal Attributes in Social Media (ACL 2014)

Journal Reviewer:

- Transactions of the Association for Computational Linguistics (TACL)
- Computational Linguistics (MIT Press)
- Transactions on Affective Computing (IEEE)
- Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research (AAAI Press)
- Information Processing Management (Elsevier)
- Social Networks (Elsevier)
- Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery (Springer)
- Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering (IEEE)
- Social Network Analysis and Mining (Springer)
- PLOS ONE (Plos.org)

Senior Program Committee:

- The Israel Science Foundation (ISF) 2018
- ICWSM 2018
- ICWSM 2017
- ICWSM 2016

Program Committee Member:

- ACL 2015 & 2016 & 2017 & 2018 (and secondary in previous years)
- WSDM 2014, 2015 & 2016
- ICWSM 2010, 2011, 2013, 2014 & 2015
- NAACL 2012, 2013, 2015 & 2016 & 2018
- EACL 2017
- WWW 2018
- CHI 2014
- EMNLP-CoNLL 2012 (best reviewer), 2013, 2015, 2016, & 2017

INVITED TALKS & TUTORIALS

- Data Mining for Business Intelligence (DMBI), Beer Sheva, Israel 2018 (Invited Talk, scheduled)
- International Conference on Law and Big Data, Ramat Gan, Israel, 2018 (Invited Talk, scheduled)
- Understanding Offline Political Systems by Mining Online Political Data, WSDM 2016, San Francisco, CA, 2016 (Tutorial)
- Data Swap, Boston, MA, 2013 (Tutorial)
- IBM Research Machine Learning and Data Mining group, Tel Aviv, Israel, 2012 (Invited Talk)
- Microsoft Research, Herzelia, Israel, 2012 (Invited Talk)
- IBM Machine Learning Day, Haifa, Israel, 2010 (Invited Talk)

TEACHING/TA

- Language Processing and Social Dynamics, Spring 2018 (scheduled)
- Natural language Processing, Fall 2017
- Introduction to Computer Science and Object Oriented Programming (TA & lecturer)
- Programming Languages (TA & lecturer)
- Information Retrieval (TA)
- Data Mining (lecturer)

Lecturer: Teaching the course syllabus as the main lecturer.

TA: Reviewing class materials with in-depth examples and defining (and sometimes grading) home work assignments.

Industry Experience

Research Scientist, IBM research, Jan 2013- Aug 2013

Machine Learning and Data Mining group (Working on the Watson Debater)

Data Mining and NLP consultant to startup companies 2011-2013

Research intern, Yahoo! Research August-December, 2010

Working on Yahoo Answers.

Product manager, New Standard Telephony (NST), 2004-5

R&D Software Engineer, Intel, 2000–2002

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Computer Science, (completed: spring 2013)

Institution: The Hebrew University Supervision: Prof. Ari Rappoport

Dissertation: Aspects of Computational Linguistics and Social Dynamics in Online User

Generated Content

MSc. in Logic and Computer Science with Honors distinction (2004),

Institute of Logic Language and Computation (ILLC), The University of Amsterdam

Supervision: Prof. Maarten de Rijke & Prof. Khalil Sima'an. Thesis: Definitional Question-Answering Using Trainable Classifiers

B.Sc. in Computer Science, The Hebrew University, School of Computer Science (2002)

B.A. in Business Administration, The Hebrew University, School of Business Administration (2002)

[Last updated: December 15, 2017]